Finding Aid for Linda Kay Tanner Strodtman papers 1966-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Linda Kay Tanner Strodtman papers 1966-1992
Strodtman, Linda K.
861073 Aa 2
Assistant professor of nursing and clinical nurse specialist at the University of Michigan. Subject files relating to her professional activities; and photographs.
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received form Linda Strodtman (Donor No. 7130 ) in a series of accessions beginning in 1984.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research with the exception of a Patient Log Book which is closed until 2082 in compliance with patient confidentiality requirements.
Linda Kay Tanner Strodtman was born on March 24, 1944 in Reno, Nevada. She earned a nursing diploma in 1965 from Hurley Hospital School of Nursing in Flint, Michigan. A B.S. in Nursing from Michigan State University followed in 1967 and a M.S. in Medical-Surgical Nursing from the University of Michigan in 1970.
Strodtman began her teaching career in 1967 as an assistant instructor at Hurley. She was an assistant professor of nursing in the University of Michigan's School of Nursing from 1972 to 1974, and began over ten years of supervising nursing graduate students doing research and clinical practicums. Strodtman also was active during the 1970s as a guest lecturer for School of Public Health courses and at nursing conferences.
Strodtman's addresses, as well as her research work, were generally on diabetes, her clinical specialty, specifically the education of diabetic patients. In 1970 she was appointed a Clinical Nurse Specialist (CNS) in Endocrinology and Metabolism at the University Hospitals; she was one the first three CNSs at the hospital. A CNS is "a Masters prepared practitioner who utilizes advanced knowledge, clinical competencies, and research in a specialized area of nursing practice."
When the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) was established in 1977, Strodtman was appointed a CNS at the center's Diabetes Center Unit (DCU). The DCU was the principal training and demonstration program core facility--a model patient care unit, employed to implement new care procedures and give practical training to health care professionals. Strodtman was one of the original members of the MDRTC's Executive Committee, first chair of the DCU's Care Program and Development Group, and member of the DCU's Operating Committee, Health Professional Education Committee, and Research Coordinating Committee.
In addition to her work with diabetic patients in the DCU, Strodtman was active in defining the roles of CNSs in general. She has written and spoken on nursing assessment procedures, primary care nursing, nursing research, and peer review. She served on several committees concerned with defining research guidelines for CNSs.
Strodtman has been committed to documenting the history of nursing. In addition to gathering the papers that constitute the current collection, she has completed a Ph.D. in the history of nursing, is active in the University of Michigan Nursing History Society, and has overseen the creation of a collection of nursing equipment and uniforms.
The papers of Linda Strodtman relate primarily to her work with diabetic patients at the University of Michigan Hospitals and to her more general involvement with Clinical Nurse Specialists (CNS) during the years, 1970-1985. There is scant material on Strodtman's personal life. There are few documents in the collection relating to her research and teaching duties.
What the collection does document is Strodtman's work with diabetic patients, her involvement with the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) and Diabetes Center Unit (DCU), and her activities as a CNS. The arrangement of the papers represents a blend of Strodtman's original order and description and series ordered by the processors. While this hybrid arrangement seeks to highlight aspects of her career, the researcher should note that series divisions are not absolute; some materials in the CNS series may relate to the MDRTC and vice versa.
The researcher is advised to be flexible and persistent in using the Strodtman collection; related materials are in separate and distinct areas of the collection. Furthermore, materials related to the MDRTC, the DCU, and nursing in general can be found in other collections held by the Bentley Library: The Diabetes Research and Training Center, School of Nursing, and Medical-Surgical Nursing Area collections all contain related materials.
The papers are organized into fourteen series:
Correspondence, 1970-1985
Self-Evaluations, Progress Data, and Logs, 1970-1983
Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC), 1976-1986
Diabetes Center Unit (DCU), 1975-1983
University of Michigan Hospitals, Early Diabetes Program, 1970-1976
University of Michigan Hospitals, Clinical Nurse Specialists (CNS), 1971-1983
University of Michigan Hospitals, Nursing Services, 1975-1979
Professional Activities, 1973-1988
Photographs
Medical Nursing Area Meetings, 1979-1984
Diabetes Patient Education Program, DCU, 1973-1983
Educational Service for Nursing (ESN) 1978-1985
School f Nursing and Nursing Services, U-M Hospitals, 1980-1992
Patient Log Book, 1972-1982
The papers were received in several accession and several series are subdivided into subseries reflecting multiple accessions.
Subjects:
Fajans, Stefan S.; Floyd, John C., 1927-; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Diabetes Research and Training Center.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical-Surgical Nursing Area.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Correspondence 1970-1985
  The Correspondence, 1970-1985 series is rather skimpy. Much of the correspondence consists of routine requests for data on the DCU program; these have been preserved since they contain information on diabetes programs at other hospitals. There are some memos on the organization of nursing services at the University of Michigan Hospitals. Overall this series indicates the range of Strodtman's activities, but provides little depth of ken.
  - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - 1982-1985 (Box 1)
- Self-Evaluation, Progress Data, and Logs 1970-1983
  The Self-Evaluations, Progress Data, and Logs, 1970-1983 series contains both day-by-day logs of Strodtman's nursing of diabetic patients, and summaries of her nursing goals and performance over six month periods. These document provide an in-depth firsthand account of the evolving duties of a CNS, and may give some indication of how these duties, and the regimen of the hospital's diabetes program, evolved over a decade.
  - July 1970-September 1970 (Box 1)
  - October 1970-February 1971 (Box 1)
  - February 1971-April 1971 (Box 1)
  - January 1972-December 1972 (Box 1)
  - May 1973-June 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1978-1983 (Box 1)
- Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) 1976-1986
  The Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) is organized in two subseries: 1976-1983 and 1980-1986 reflecting materials received and processed in separate accessions
  - 1976-1983
    The 1976-1983 subseries documents one of the first of five programs funded by a 1977 HEW grant to explore inter-disciplinary approaches to the study and treatment of digestive and metabolic diseases, specifically diabetes. Stefan S. Fajans, director of MDRTC, believed this approach was the most fruitful way to "apply more effectively to the patient" what has been and will be learned about the disease. The MDRTC established three core programs--Continuing Education and Outreach (CEDO), Training and Demonstration, and Research-- and eleven core facilities. This series includes Strodtman's report to Nursing Service on the MDRTC grant proposal, which discusses both the center and the role of nurses in it at some length. Also important are the Executive Committee materials (1977-1982) which include a 1977 critique of the proposal by HEW and a 1982 review by the NIH. The Educational Policy Committee materials document the center's efforts to monitor ongoing educational programs for health care providers. Materials on public outreach and education can be found in the Regional Advisory Committee files and in the newsletter.
    - Initial Nursing Service Involvement 1976-1977
      - Committees (Minutes and Memos) 1977-1982
        - Executive 1977-1982
          - 1977 (Box 1)
          - 1978 (Box 1)
          - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
          - 1980 (Box 1)
          - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Educational Policy 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Regional Advisory 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - NIAMDD Site Visit 1977 (Box 1)
    - Professional Education and Training Group 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1986
    The MDRTC, 1980-1986 subseries continues documentation begun by previous accessions. The subseries includes files on the Diabetes Center Unit and the Continuing Education and Outreach Core (CEDO), an arm of the MDRTC devoted to furthering the education of diabetic care-givers. The latter contains course materials for continuing education graduate classes that CEDO helped organize in conjunction with Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education and others.
    - Committee minutes, memos, etc.
      - Planning Committee 1985-1986 (Box 6)
      - Policy Committee 1983-1985 (Box 6)
    - Ligand Core and Biochemistry Core Facilities (cost studies) 1985 (Box 6)
    - National Institute of Health Site Visit Team Report (regarding MDRTC funding renewal) 1982 (Box 6)
    - Newsletter 1978, 1981, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Pilot Feasibility Applications and Grants (Scientific Review Committee?) 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Diabetes Center Unit (DCU)
      - DCU Guidelines and Profiles 1979-1985 (Box 6)
      - Diabetes Education Profile Tool 1980 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous 1983-1985 (Box 6)
      - Post-employment Nurse Survey 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Progress Reports 1978-1982, 1984-1985, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Continuing Education and Outreach Core (CEDO), MDRTC
      - CEDO Baseline Data Collection Instruments 1980 (Box 7)
      - "A Profile of Psychological Adjustment in Diabetes," 1980 (Box 7)
      - A Symposium and Preceptorship in Diabetes Care 1982 (Box 7)
      - Symposium on Diabetes (Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education) 1980 (Box 7)
      - Diabetes Update(Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education) 1983 (Box 7)
      - Rehabilitation Patient Care Unit 1972-1982 (Box 7)
- Diabetes Center Unit (DCU), MDRTC 1975-1983
  The Diabetes Center Unit (DCU), MDRTC, 1977-1983 series documents the activities of the DCU. This unit was created to implement model diabetic patient care, to serve as a laboratory for studies of diabetics, and to give health care professional on-the-job training in the latest diabetic care techniques. John C. Floyd was the center's first director; he also served as coordinator of the DCU's parent unit within MDRTC, the Training and Demonstration Program. Strodtman chaired the DCU's Operating Committee and served on the other committees represented in this series. The strengths of the DCU series are the Committee Minutes, the Progress Reports, and Standards of Care. The terse minutes of the Operating Committee provide an overview of the unit; the Research Coordinating Committee and the Health Professional Education Committee provide the fullest documentation of these crucial functions within the DCU. The Progress Reports, prepared by Fajans, outline unit objectives, five-year plans, and rigorous self-assessments. Materials in the Standard of Care folder, some of which was created by Strodtman, addresses the defining of optimal goals and procedures for patient care.
  Perhaps the central concern of the DCU was educating diabetic patients in self-care to promote proper control of the disease. The Diabetes Patient Education Program, DCU, 1975-1983 series documents this effort with knowledge tests, handouts, and patient memos. This series also contains materials on internal and external evaluations of the efficacy of patient education programs.
  - Origins: Model Demonstration Unit
    - Proposal, Objectives, Staff 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Patient Needs (Mary Ann Swain) 1977 (Box 2)
  - Admission Guidelines (Box 2)
  - Renewal of Funding Proposal 1981 (Box 2)
  - Committees 1978-1983 (Box 2)
    - Operating Committee 1980-1983, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Health Professional Educational Committee 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Research Coordinating 1978-1980, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Standards of Care 1977-1978, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1980-1983
    - Replacement of Strodtman 1983 (Box 2)
    - Telephone System 1980 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Patient Materials
    - Orientation (Box 2)
    - Diabetes Knowledge Tests (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Evaluations 1978-1982
    - Internal 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - External Consultant's Review 1979 (Box 2)
    - Outpatient Education Planning 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Educational Materials 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Patient Education Workshop/Symposium 1975 (Box 2)
  - Proposed Publication of Teaching Outlines 1983 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- University of Michigan Hospitals, Early Diabetes Program 1970-1976
  The University of Michigan Hospitals, Early Diabetes Program, 1970-1976 series contains nursing care plans, patient statistics, and patient education notes for the four years preceding the establishment of the MDRTC.
  - Standard Nursing Care Plans 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Patient Statistics 1970-1976 (Box 2)
  - Patient Education 1973-1976
    - Guides for Teachers 1973-1976 (Box 2)
    - Class Outlines (Box 2)
- University of Michigan Hospitals, Clinical Nurse Specialists (CNS) 1971-1983
  The University of Michigan Hospitals, Clinical Nurse Specialists (CNS), 1971-1982 series documents the CNS program nearly from its 1970 inception; Strodtman was one of three original CNS appointees. The series contains two early (1971) progress reports on the program, a proposal to expand clinical nursing opportunities, and surveys of CNSs. The Management by Objective reports, semi-annual descriptions of how each nurse met her responsibilities, provide telling insights into the specific activities of CNSs.
  - Position Descriptions/Definitions 1970s-1983 (Box 2)
  - Internal Studies and Evaluations 1971-1982
    - Progress Reports 1971 (Box 2)
    - Career Program Reports 1972 (Box 3)
    - Task Force 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Monthly Meetings 1981 (Box 3)
  - Management By Objective Reports 1976-1983
    - Descriptions of Responsibility (Box 3)
    - MBO Reports of Various Nurses (Box 3)
    - MBO Reports of Linda Strodtman 1976-1983 (Box 3)
  - Workshops/Symposia 1971-1981
    - University of Michigan Hospitals 1971 (Box 3)
    - Out-of-State 1972-1982 (Box 3)
    - Peer Review 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Honoring Marjorie Jackson 1981 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1977-1980
    - "Meet a CNS" (Articles in Staff Nursing Newsletter) 1980 (Box 3)
    - Collective Bargaining 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Staffing Shortages 1978 (Box 3)
    - Abstracts of CNS's Research 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Articles and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- University of Michigan Hospitals, Nursing Services 1975-1979
  The University of Michigan Hospitals, Nursing Services, 1975-1979 series documents the general nursing activities of Strodtman. Of special note are the materials of the Strodtman-chaired Research Review and Study Committee, which functioned to "facilitate the conduct of nursing research," to review research proposals, and to promote the "incorporation of research findings into clinical nursing practice, management, and education at University Hospital." Strodtman was also active on the Interdisciplinary Task Force, which examined the impact of cross-disciplinary approaches on the quality of care, and she was involved with the Nursing Care Crises of 1979 which raised questions concerning the proper relationship between the School of Nursing and the Hospitals' Nursing Services.
  - Structural Review 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Research Review and Study Committee 1977-1980
    - Purpose and Membership 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Memos 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Presentation to Graduate Students 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Interdisciplinary Task Force 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Nursing Care Crisis 1979 (Box 3)
  - Reentry Program for Inactive Nurses 1979 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Professional Activities 1972-1988
  The Professional Activities, 1972-1988 consists of three separate accessions of material documenting Strodtman's work in professional organizations, as a lecturer, consultant and researcher. The 1972-1983 subseries contains scattered materials on Strodtman's research work, her guest lecturing, her supervision of practicums, and her work as a consultant.
  The1980-1988 subseries includes files on Correspondence, Projects and Reports, and Speaking Engagements. The introduction of microcomputers into nursing practices was a primary research interest of Strodtman's in the years documented by this series.
  - 1972-1983
    - Studies and Papers 1973-1980
      - 1973 Urine Testing Study (Box 4)
      - 1978 Study of Patient Education Materials (Box 4)
      - 1979 Study of Different Patient Education Materials (Box 4)
      - 1980 Abstracts of Papers of American Diabetes Association (Box 4)
    - Teaching and Supervising 1974-1982
      - 1974 Health Education Practicum (Box 4)
      - 1976 Field Observation of Patient Education (Box 4)
      - 1978 Education of Patients in the Health Care System (HBE 684, two sessions) (Box 4)
      - 1980-1981 Nursing Related to Metabolic Function (N618) (Box 4)
      - 1982 Nursing Practicum (Box 3)
    - Consultation Visits to Diabetes Care Centers
      - 1979-1980 Providence Hospital, Southfield, MI (Box 4)
      - 1982 Oakwood Hospital, Dearborn, MI (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - 1975-1983
    - American Diabetes Association, Michigan Affiliate (Youth Committee and Board of Directors) 1980-1985 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Joint Practice Committee 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Nurses Association 1975-1982
      - "Does Special Care Warrant Special Costs?" [Strodtman paper] 1975 (Box 4)
      - Negotiations 1975 (Box 4)
      - Council for Expanded Nursing Practice 1976-1980 (Box 4)
  - 1980-1988
    - Correspondence 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - Projects and reports
      - "A Study of Health Results of Two Diabetic Care Programs" (Floyd, Davis) 1980 (Box 5)
      - "Microcomputer Training Program of Diabetic Diet" (Knopf, et al) 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - "Microcomputer Based Data Management System for Nursing Assessment of the Diabetic Patient" (Abdoo, et al; presented at Fifth Annual Computer Applications in Medical Care Symposium, Washington, D. C.) 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - "An Automated Clinical Information System for the DCU" (Ozbolt, Schultz, Strodtman) 1981 (Box 6)
      - "Microcomputer Assisted Training in Principles of Diabetic Diets" (Knopf, et al) 1981-1982 (Box 6)
      - "Microcomputer Generated Nursing Reports Based on Computerized Nursing Assessment" (Abdoo, et al) 1982 (Box 6)
      - Nursing Computerized Database 1980-1982 (Box 6)
      - "Nursing Care of Patients with Diabetes Mellitus Who Are Hospitalized on Medical Units other than the Diabetes Center Unit" 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Speaking engagements 1975-1986, 22 folders (Box 6)
- Photographs circa 1976
  - CNS Rounds, University of Michigan Hospitals 1976 (Box 4)
- Medical Nursing Area Meetings 1979-1984
  The Medical Area Nursing minutes document Strodtman's participation in the management of this area of the hospital; they can be seen to be roughly analogous to the materials in the MDRTC and DCU series of the earlier accession.
  - 1979 (Box 4)
  - 1980 (Box 4)
  - 1981 (Box 4)
  - 1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1984 (Box 4)
- Patient Education 1973-1983
  The Patient Education series is directly and immediately linked to the materials of the Diabetes Patient Education Program, DCU, 1978-1982 series. Similarly the Professional Activities series parallels the Miscellaneous Professional Activities series of the earlier accession.
  - Survey 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Conference [Carbondale, IL] June 1974 (Box 4)
  - "Effects of a Teaching Tool on Urine Testing in Patients with Diabetes" 1974 (Box 4)
  - Booklet Introduction 1978-1983 (Box 4)
- Educational Services for Nursing (ESN), University of Michigan Hospitals 1978-1985
  The ESN series documents nursing practices and training procedures at the University Hospital through a series of educational programs consisting of photographic slides with accompanying audio cassettes.
  - Slides with audio cassettes, 9 folders
    - Problem-oriented Record 1978 (Box 4)
    - I. V. Placement and Therapy for Patients 1979-1982 (Box 4)
    - Nursing Care of the Burned Child 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Nurse's Guide to Bronchoscopy 1984 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan Hospital Disaster Plan 1985 (Box 5)
    - A Tour of University Hospital for Nursing Staff Orientation 1985 (Box 5)
    - Acuity Classification undated (Box 5)
    - Nurse's Role in CVP Line Insertion undated (Box 5)
    - Patient Charge System undated (Box 5)
    - ESN Manual 1985 (Box 5)
- School of Nursing and Nursing Services, University of Michigan Hospitals 1980-1992
  The series, School of Nursing and Nursing Services, University of Michigan Hospitals, contains materials that Kathryn Fischer and Strodtman collected from various committees and offices in the 1980s and early 1990s. Because it was sometimes difficult to determine whether the School of Nursing or Nursing Services (or both) created the documents, and because the materials shed little light on either Fischer's or Strodtman's career, the records were kept together in one series. Records easily available in other Bentley Library collections (see those listed above) were eliminated; the remaining files comprise a convenient gathering of committee work relating to nursing in the decade.
  - Administrative memos 1984 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Society
    - Fall 1985 Reunion (Box 5)
    - Subcommittee on Referring Physician Relations (Box 5)
  - Annual reports (various School of Nursing committees and offices) 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Committee minutes, agendas, etc.
    - Faculty Workload Committee 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Medical-Surgical Area 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - Medical Nursing Dress Code Committee 1985 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Planning Group for 25th Anniversary Medical-Surgical and PMHN (Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing?) Master Programs 1985 (Box 5)
  - Clinical Nurse Specialist meetings 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Faculty meetings and memos August 1991-June 1992, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Patient Log Book 1972-1982
  The Patient Log Book from the University of Michigan Rehabilitation Patient Care Unit demonstrates primarily an admissions record-keeping system over the course of a decade, before computerized databases replaced hand-written ledgers.
  - University Of Michigan Rehabilitation Patient Care Unit, 1972-1982 (Box 8)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2082 ]